Hi, everyone, welcome to this new video.
So in this video, we are going to discuss about the limitations of Dijkstra's algorithm.
So what are the limitations?
So Dijkstra's algorithm has one limitation, that it does not work for integrity, which.
So if your graph contains any negative edge, then it will not work.
What do I mean by negative?
I mean negative with light.
So Dijkstra algorithm only only only works for the positive weight that is positive agist.
If your graph contain any one negative, which then does extraordinarily Nordberg, why it will not
work.
Let's try to find out this.
So let's say it is my source Vertex and I want to find out what this stands for BNC from Vertex.
So again, what I'm going to do is distance is zero distance infinity, distance infinity.
So zero plus three is less than infinity.
So I will change it to three zero plus four is less than infinity.
So I will change it to four now.
Four and three.
Which one is minimum.
I think four is minimum rate.
And also the remark that nobody has been visited nor has been visited.
So four and three which one is minimum.
So three is minimum, right.
Three years minimum.
So 40 go to its neighbor so it doesn't have any other neighbor.
Right.
This is Director Graph.
This is one big graph, not bidirectional.
These edges are not bidirectional.
They are union directional.
So B doesn't have any other neighbors.
Bill doesn't have any neighbors.
So I cannot go anywhere.
So this node has been visited.
This node has been visited.
Now let's talk about this vertex C, so C has one neighbor, which is B, so C has one neighbor, which
is B, but B has already been visited.
So we will not do anything and C doesn't have any other neighbors.
So I am done.
Now let's see that our answer is correct or not.
So C think minimum distance will be four which is correct.
I can only reach C with this pot.
So minimum distance phone is correct.
B using the minimum distance from Vertex is three.
But that is wrong.
Y because the minimum distance is to vital.
If you will come here first four and then if you come here to forward minus two will be two.
If you will come B via C then the distance will be two.
Ideally the answer should have been two, but Dijkstra is saying the distance is three digits, facing
the distance is three.
So that's why Dijkstra algorithm gives a wrong answer for negative edges.
So if your graph contains any negative, which if your graph contains any negative it, then Dijkstra
will give you a wrong answer.
Dijkstra will give you a wrong answer.
That's delimitation of Dijkstra algorithm and how we can improve this, so what algorithm we can use.
So there is one more algorithm, Bellmon for algorithm, so for algorithm works for negative EDG.
Also, Bellmon algorithm will work for Negrita, which also so this algorithm is not so much important
from university point of view and also from interview point of view.
So if you want to read about this algorithm, you can definitely go through this algorithm.
Very pretty simple algorithm.
You can check this out yourself.
And if you face any problem, do let me know.
I will make a video of it.
Right.
So that is the limitation of Dijkstra algorithm, that it will not work for negativities.
It will give you the wrong answer.
And if you want if the graph contains negative images, you want to find out the right solution, then
Bellmon for algorithm is the way to go.
So that's pretty much all that I want to cover in this video, so I will meet you in the next one.
Thank you.